<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The controversie debated about the reuerend gesture of kneeling in the act of receiuing the holy communion. By Iames Wats, minister of Gods word at Woodnosborough in Kent: and sometime fellow of Magdalene Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Wats, James, d. 1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838469</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1121:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The controversie debated about the reuerend gesture of kneeling in the act of receiuing the holy communion. By Iames Wats, minister of Gods word at Woodnosborough in Kent: and sometime fellow of Magdalene Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Wats, James, d. 1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. I[aggard] for Walter Burre, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 283) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise concerning kneeling at the communion.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Posture in worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONTROVERSIE DEBATED About the Reuerend <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Kneeling, in the Act of</hi> Receiuing the Holy Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IAMES WATS, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Gods Word at <hi>Woodnosborough</hi> in <hi>Kent:</hi> And ſometime fellow of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>HEB DDIM HEB DDIEV</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William Jaggard</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by W. I. for Walter Burre, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the ſigne of the Crane, 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND and Right Worshipfull <hi>M. Doctor Boys, Deane of Christ-Church in Canterbury, all prosperity</hi> and happineſſe in the LORD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerend Sir:</hi> Albeit I am conſcious to my ſelfe of my inability to anſwer the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion your loue long ſince hath conceiued of ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in me for improuements of a Scholler: yet cannot <hi>Salomons</hi> word, being repreſented now to my thought <hi>(Stultus reputabitur ſapiens ſi ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit)</hi> diſhearten me from imparting ſuch of my meditations vnto you, as ſome of them a good while ſince, and ſome more lately I had written downe, to ſatisfie (if I might) ſome ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous
<pb facs="tcp:2850:3"/>conſciences, touching the lawfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient vſe of the geſture of Kneeling in the Acte of receiuing the holy Euchariſt. About the ſigne of the Croſſe in or after the other Sacrament, I had filled many ſheetes of paper, before I could reade much of the more accurate writings of other men in that argument, and being loth according to the old Adage, to make that all onely my Cipreſſe tree: I vndertook vpon earneſt requeſt of a friend (more profitable I hope to the Church in his labours, then I can be) to ſhew the vanity of one who gloriouſly boaſts in print, to make proofe; that the controuerted ceremonies are defended by no other arguments, then are vſed by Papiſts, and which by elder Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants haue bene long ſince anſwered. Betweene his ſecond (though <hi>Senior Ignoto</hi> to me) and my ſelfe, the ſame was drawne ſo oft in writing <hi>con</hi> and <hi>pro,</hi> that yet I am not aſhamed to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to any vpon what termes I left him. Then an occaſion was offered mee to anſwer ſome <hi>Quaeres</hi> about kneeling, and afterwardes more cloſely to ioyne iſſue for repelling all the Obiections which I haue obſerued in reading, and which for the moſt part haue bin vrged in conferring with mee. My
<pb facs="tcp:2850:3"/>arguments and anſwers ſuch as they be, I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that I can get no reply to them: yet I doe not perceiue, that any one formerly oppoſite is willing to yeeld himſelfe perſwaded by them. And for this cauſe partly I preſent &amp; ſubmit them to your reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend cenſure, whether contempt, or ſome more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wermeetest to be ſet againſt them. Partly, for that I am ſlow in extemporary ſpeech, and ſo as is nothing likely to purchaſe an opinion of more iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or vnderstanding in me: therefore I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let my pen run as you ſee, then inter <hi>Vocales et reales amicos,</hi> to be still <hi>realiter a mute.</hi> I gratulate vnfeinedly your dignity, and no leſſe the comfort of your owne ſoule, and eſteeme in Gods Church, by your learned and godly labours publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed: my deſire is to adhere to you ſtill in all ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of loue, and that with ingenuity: neither ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing nor expecting any thing elſe, but your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and encouragements, as formerly you haue vouchſafed me. The God of heauen grant vnto you many comfortable yeares to help to ſupport his truth with <hi>Sions</hi> peace, and them that ſtand for both. So I rest. <hi>Ian. 1. 1619.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips moſt affectionate to be commanded,</hi> Iames Wattes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>QVi genua, admiſſus menſae conuiua tremendae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flectere neſcit (&amp; hoc neſcire eſt nolle proteruis)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prauum, quod didicit, dediſcere diſcat; &amp; harum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Queis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ineſt, rationum ponderepreſſus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Submittat rigidos curuato poplite neruos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pondus habent haec tela; grauant, frangunt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> columnas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Se non flectentes. Lector, ſi for ſitan anceps,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ceſſure, Vale, vel reſponſure Reſponſis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>De hoc libello ſic iudicat.
<signed>T.G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTROVERSIE debated about the geſture mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to be vſed in our Church, of the <hi>members thereunto pertaining, in the act of</hi> receiuing the holy Supper of the Lord; by way of Demands or Oppoſitions, with Solutions and Anſwers adioyning to them; and in ſuch forme and order as the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are wont commonly to be propounded.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it lawfull to kneele (in receiuing) when Chriſt ſitting, did adminiſter to his Diſciples, and they alſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſitting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by this queſtion it cannot be ſuppoſed that Communicants ſhould receiue ſitting, except wee alſo in adminiſtring, vſe the ſame geſture,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:5"/>which in none of our Churches is, or well can be obſerued.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Math. 26.20.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luk 22 14.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Chriſt and his Diſciples did not ſit as our manner is, but it ſeemeth they lay leaning one vpon anothers boſome; for which ſee <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob. 13.25.</hi> Not as it is ſaide of him when hee preached ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Matth. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 23. with the note vpon it. Whereunto I adde, that all the words vſed in the Originall doe ſignifie either lying, or falling down, and not ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: therefore if his example were intended to be a patterne for geſture not to be changed, why would we haue it changed into ſitting after our faſhion, and ſo argue againſt kneeling hereby?</p>
            <p>Obiection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We muſt follow Christs example, in that hee and his did obſerue the vſuall geſture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>But muſt we thinke he obſerued It, becauſe it was the vſuall geſture in receiuing other meats? nay rather, ſeeing wee muſt come with another minde and affection, and with another inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as not deſiring food for the body, but for the ſoule) how can it be thought, that he would eſpecially commend the common geſture to be vſed now, which is vſed at taking ordinary ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the body? It may rather be conceiued that our Sauiour did reſpect to obſerue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon geſture which the Iewiſh Church did then vſe in celebrating the Paſſeouer. From whence the argument followes ſtrongly to vrge, that we ſhould all conforme our ſelues to the vſuall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb facs="tcp:2850:5"/>of this our Church in receiuing alſo: for ſhall Chriſt and his Apoſtles obſerue the common geſture with the Church of the Iewes: and ſhall not we obſerue the common geſture of the Church, whereof we are members? ſhall his example that way (tending to peace and vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie) be of no force therein to ſway vs?</p>
            <p>Inſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which Christ did, howſoeuer, we are ſure was beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reply.</p>
            <p>Yet (as is ſuppoſed) he varied in communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Paſſeouer from the preſcript order ſet downe in the Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 11. which was, to be girt, and ſhod, with ſtaues in their hands; and therefore ſtanding, (as Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> vpon that place, by thoſe circumſtances, and by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent teſtimony proueth). Now if it be credible that this geſture was changeable after it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned: how much more the geſture which Chriſt did vſe and his Apoſtles, the ſame onely being reported to vs, and no commandement ſet downe for vs at all?</p>
            <p>Obiection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſay ſtill, Chriſt his doing and approbation then, hath the force of a perpetuall command, concerning vs, and to binde vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>This aſſertion is many wayes liable to excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for when the Lord ſaid (<hi>This doe, Luk.</hi> 22.19.
<pb facs="tcp:2850:6"/>19. 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.24.) it muſt needs be, hee reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſubſtance, and not preciſely the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: therefore the Miniſter communicating vnto others is not allowed, nor at any hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſit. Secondly, whereas hee alwaies himſelfe receiues firſt, Chriſts owne example will not warrant. Thirdly (to omit difference of number in Communicants from his number, and difference of ſexe) who doubts but that it is fitteſt to receiue in the publique place of Gods worſhip, though the firſt celebration were in a priuate chamber? and that it is fitteſt to receiue in the fore-noone, and before dinner, albeit the time then were after ſupper, and not then onely, but long afterward? as <hi>Acts ch.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. the breaking of bread was (it ſeemeth) after the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note place="margin">1. Cor: 11.21.</note> and ſo after midnight. Likewiſe in <hi>Corinth</hi> euery one tooke his owne Supper before, which the Apoſtle there reprooues, onely in reſpect of the exceſſe, and of ſuch banqueting in the Church, and of vncharitableneſſe towards the poor; not in reſpect of the time, &amp; therfore doth expreſſely mention the time of Chriſts inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to haue beene in the night, by and by after, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. Now ſeeing we hold all thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may vary from the firſt inſtitution, why muſt onely the ſame geſture be obſeru'd, which (as I ſhewed before) is not the ſame but in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality? A common geſture ye preſſe ſtill muſt be vſed as Chriſt did vſe it; wherein wee would
<pb facs="tcp:2850:6"/>ioyne with you, if yee meant common by the Churches vſe in receiuing; but of that before.</p>
            <p>Obiection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſts inſtitution, and the practiſe of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles may bee vrged against kneeling, becauſe they were not required to kneele: neither did they ſo at receiuing, when hee himſelfe was preſent, and did miniſter vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>This ſhall be anſwered more directly, when a like obiection will come in againe. Firſt then I now reply, that the words are (<hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 26. and <hi>Marke</hi> 14.22.) <hi>As they did eat, Ieſus tooke bread, &amp;c.</hi> not as they did ſit, or as they did lye, &amp;c. ſo that our Sauiours practiſe muſt needs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a ſtronger argument for a neceſſitie of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſomewhat before (which is expreſſed) then for receiuing by ſuch or ſuch a poſition of the body, which is not expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing the bread was broken to them, <hi>as they did eate,</hi> and as their manner of ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or lying was to eate: wee ſee (I thinke) a plaine difference, how we may kneele more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently in receiuing (as the ſeats bee fitted for vs) then they could.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the argument from Chriſt his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe (miniſtring to them who did not kneele) to vrge a neceſſitie, as if therefore we may not kneele: is a plaine fallacy: as if one ſhould ſay, Chriſt did vſually preach ſitting (as <hi>Math.</hi> 4.1.
<pb facs="tcp:2850:7"/>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 2. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.20.) therefore we may not preach ſtanding: or, he is noted to haue preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtanding but once, therefore we may not doe ſo often: or thus, Chriſt did preach many times, but we reade yet onely of one time wherein he tooke a Text.
<note place="margin">Luk. 4. v. 16.</note> So wee ſhould doe beſt to preach commonly without taking of a Text.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſeeing the Lord Ieſus is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to vs for an enſample, not onely in his manner of performing the parts of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but in all manner of conuerſation, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.15. (excepting what appertained to his diuine nature, or to his offices) therefore as well, ſeeing he choſe to be poore, we muſt refuſe to be rich. As he wore a coate without ſeame, ſo we muſt haue no ſeame in our vpper garment. And thus, way may be made for the ſpirit of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to trouble the whole Church of God, and euery member of it.</p>
            <p>Obiection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But we marueile ſtill, if this geſture of kneeling were to be allowed: why all reformed Churches doe diſallow it, &amp; that it is vſed only among the Papiſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>The geſture among the Papiſts (which ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, was commanded firſt by Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third) was kneeling not at receiuing,
<note place="margin">Balaeus de actis Rom. pontif. l. 5 pag. 279.</note> but at the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuation or lifting vp of the Maſſe-cake or hoaſt (as they tearme it) ouer the Prieſts head, that all ſhould then together fall downe and adore it:
<pb facs="tcp:2850:7"/>but we haue no ſuch kneeling, becauſe we haue no ſuch eleuation, nor we haue no ſuch hoaſt to eleuate, but in our hearts we abandon it: yet can we imagine no other, but that the members of the Church (ſeuerally) in time of receiuing, did kneele of ancient time, becauſe of theſe and the like ſayings of the Fathers that then liued;
<note place="margin">Cyprian ad Quirinum. l. 3. cap. 94.</note> as that the Euchariſt with feare and honour is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and that it is to be diſcerned and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from other meates,
<note place="margin">Auguſt in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 118.</note> 
               <hi>veneratione ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter debita;</hi> by a veneration ſingularly due vnto it. And, at this day,
<note place="margin">Hodie in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteris adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus carnem Chriſt. Amb. diſpu. Sanct. lib. 3. cap. 12.</note> we adore Chriſts fleſh in the myſteries, which (being a ſentence, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts alleadge againſt the Church of England) Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> anſweres (<hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 537. in 8.) Verily, and ſo doe we, we adore Chriſt in them, we adore not the myſteries themſelues; which muſt needes be <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his meaning, becauſe he ſaid a little before (neither doe we reade that any thing is to be adored beſides God.)
<note place="margin">Neque adoratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quicquam prater deum legimus.</note> 
               <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> alſo held, that Chriſt is to be adored in the Sacrament, no leſſe,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. 24. in cap. 16. ad Corinth.</note> 
               <hi>cum reuerentia &amp; tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> with reuerence and trembling, then as the wiſe men did performe to him lying in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. which we ſee there plainely was by kneeling. But if theſe and like ſayings of the Ancients, ſhould either be ſuſpected or contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we refuſe not the iudgement of Churches reformed now adayes, and of the godly learned in them. The Church of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:8"/>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1575. as they ſay firſt, <hi>Hoc ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, &amp;c.</hi> This ſacrament ought to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred and receiued without adoration, and the worſhip which is due to God onely: ſo they ſay by and by after,
<note place="margin">Populus fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium vſitatiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in genuo procumbens hoc accipit.</note> The faithfull people moſt vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue this, falling downe vpon their knees with giuing of thankes, and reioycing, &amp; himns, and rehearſall of benefits, by the death of Chriſt; and all this (as they vnderſtand) according to Chriſts bidding, <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> The <hi>Heluetians</hi> alſo in their confeſſion (<hi>pag.</hi> 113.) to cleare themſelues from hauing a meane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,
<note place="margin">Sunt enim haeres ſanctae &amp; venerandae.</note> 
               <hi>de ſacris ſymbolis,</hi> of the holy ſignes, they ſay thus of them, Theſe are things holy and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable. And the cenſure (in the name of the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> and of the low-Countries) giuen vpon thoſe words of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (falling downe vpon their knees) it is this:
<note place="margin">In hoc etiam ritu ſuam cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Eccleſiae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uam relinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, non quod per ſo hunc mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> In this rite alſo we thinke it meete that euery Church (they ſay not euery particular man and woman) ſhould be left entirely to their owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, not that we in it ſelfe condemne this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, &amp;c. yet thoſe Cenſurers thinke (for auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bread-worſhip) it were better in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this ceremonie of kneeling were aboliſhed. But let it alſo be remembred, that in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face they modeſtly ſubmit their iudgement (wherein they diſſent) vnto the iudgement of their brethren. Like as Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> did write concerning the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme:
<pb facs="tcp:2850:8"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Scio nonnull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſublata crucis adoratione, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem ſigni cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis vſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> retinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe. Vtanturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur ipſi ſicuti par eſt ſua li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate. Reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. ad Balduinum.</note> I know that ſome who haue abandoned the worſhipping of the Croſſe, haue yet reteyned ſome vſe of the ſigne of the Croſſe. Let them therefore as it is meet vſe their owne liberty.</p>
            <p>Obiection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We haue heard tho, that Master</hi> Beza <hi>did diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low kneeling, while the myſteries be in receiuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <p>He did ſo: howbeit not ſimply neither, but for feare of ſuperſtition; yet he confeſſeth there, that it hath
<note n="d" place="margin">Geniculatio du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſymbola ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiuntur ſpecie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem habet piae ac Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anae veneratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ac proinde olim potuit cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fructu vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pari, &amp;c. Epiſt. 12 pag. 100.</note> an appearance (not of euill, but) of godly and Chriſtian veneration or reuerence, &amp; therefore might once be vſed with fruit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. And he deriues not this cuſtome of kneeling from the Papiſts, but rather thought that their ſuperſtition and Idolatry in bread-worſhip took the beginning from this cuſtome. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vpon his former conceſſion or grant, wee ſhould need (me-thinke) no fitter vmpire then himſelfe was to be iudged by, for allowance of our vſe of kneeling; for in his laſt Epiſtle of all, his words be theſe:
<note n="e" place="margin">Huius ſeculi dies ita mali ſunt, vt ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo fere (abie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta vera Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione) cogitet de ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus reuoca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis nam ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones nunc ijs relinquuntur qus imperiti &amp; Idiota appellanter, tametſi, ad ſpeciem &amp; ſimulationem retineantur. Impietas autem &amp; religionis omnis contemptus, quod crimen ita nefarium eſt vt etiam diaboli ſint eius iudices, peſtiferum illud venenum eſt a quo te potiſsimum cauere oportet, vtpote quod in eam voraginem homines praecipitat. Epiſt. 84. Regi Nauarrae.</note> The daies are ſo euill now, that none almoſt (reiecting true religion after they haue receiued it) thinke of returning againe to ſuperſtitions. Superſtitions are now left for them that be counted ignorant &amp; ſimple, though they be ſomewhat reteyned, and counterfaited
<pb facs="tcp:2850:9"/>for a ſhew. But impiety and contempt of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (a crime ſo deteſtable, that the diuels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues may and will be Iudges of it) that is the direfull poyſon aboue all to beware of, which tumbles men headlong, and ouer-whelmes in that gulfe, whereout there is no hope of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I find ſome men forward to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vp the names of worthy neotericall Diuines in this queſtion, as if all did plainly auouch knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the act of receiuing to bee vnlawfull, I propoſe in the firſt place, the ſayings of three to be conſidered of, <hi>Oecolampadius, Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Greenham. Oecolampadius</hi> (a moſt worthy inſtrument to cauſe the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to breake forth and ſhine in the houſe of God, and to diſpell the darkeneſſe of Popery) gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his
<note n="f" place="margin">Epiſtolarum ib. 4 fol 177. ad fratres in agro Solotino.</note> aduice vnto a Church (concerning the geſture to be vſed in receiuing the Sacrament; no man being reputed to hold farther off from the adoration of it then he) ſaith thus: Some like to follow the rite of <hi>Zurich,</hi> ſome of <hi>Berne,</hi> ſome ours of <hi>Baſil,</hi> but may agree all well together, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee vſe not the ſame rite as they doe.
<note n="g" place="margin">Nunquid Chriſtus magis ſedetes ve! ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vel genu flec tentes reſpicit? At nihil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius eſſe poteſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt in vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> formulam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedatis. Non patiuntur res veſtrae vt in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus diuerſi nunc ſitis qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do aliae ſectae inter vos eſse audiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vt licet pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> momenti ſit in varietate ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniarum, apud ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, apud eos ta me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quibus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſt ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charitatis ſtudium, ſi (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictis ijs quae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident pleriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>) nouam &amp; ſingularem viam ingrediantur, neceſſe dicit vt inde ſimultatibus cauſa porrigatur. Fatemur eſſe quidem quod incaena variare non licet, vtpote &amp;c. Porro in ſecundarijs curioſiores eſſe non tam religio quam ſuperſtitio eſt. Nolumus vos in noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. ſed vobis nihil vtilius eſt conformitate quadam. Profecto vbi per oſtentatione ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularis ritus quaeritur, &amp; receditur a fratrum communs ratione, vtilius foret interim caena deſtitus, &amp;c. date (oro) operam ne ſit in vobis varietas</note> Hath Chriſt reſpect more to them that ſit, or to them that ſtand, or to them that kneele? yet
<pb facs="tcp:2850:9"/>(ſaith he againe) nothing is more behooueful for you, then to agree all in one forme among your ſelues. And although there bee ſmall weight in variety of ceremonies with them that be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, yet if ſome (who haue not ſuch a reſpect of loue and charity) ſhal leaue thoſe rites which the moſt approoue of, and enter, or goe a new way ſingular from the reſt; it muſt neceſſarily be the occaſion of ſtrife and variance. Wee confeſſe there is ſomwhat in the Lords Supper which in no caſe may bee changed, as if wee ſhould haue cheeſe offered vs in ſtead of bread, or milke in ſtead of wine, or if they ſhould change the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; turne it into a ſacrifice, or of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion make it a priuate banquet, or any other way that the ſubſtance of the Supper may bee impeached. But to be ouer-curious in ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry matters, argues not one to be religious, but rather ſuperſtitious. Wee will not draw ye to obſerue our ceremonies, nor of the Church of <hi>Zurich,</hi> nor of <hi>Berne;</hi> howbeit nothing is more profitable, then that ye do hold a conformity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelues. And then his iudgement was moreouer, that ſuch as (in the rite of receiuing) would be ſingular and odde from the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it were better they were ſhut out from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing altogether. Then hee fell to intreat thus: I pray doe your endeuour,
<note place="margin">Caueie om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino ne in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veniant Sacramenta.</note> that ye may one doe like another, and not vary or bee diuers among your ſelues; yea and ye muſt mainly beware of
<pb facs="tcp:2850:10"/>this, That the Sacraments come not into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
            <q>Whether the Lincolnſhire Miniſters in their abridgement had cauſe to alledge this worthy man, as ſtanding on their ſide, I leaue it to any ones iudgement, that ſhall compare what they alledge, with this that I haue ſet downe at large.</q>
            <p>They cite alſo <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> as being cleare on their ſide, to condemne the geſture of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Yet who ſo reades his Commentarie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the booke of <hi>Iudges</hi> imprinted at <hi>Zurich,</hi> in the ſecond chapter <hi>fol.</hi> 33. he ſhall plainely finde theſe words: I thinke wee ſhould not contend that rites and ceremonies ſhould be any where the ſame, but there muſt be this prouiſo, that all come as neere as may be to the word of God, and that edification (with decent order) may be furthered;
<note place="margin">Nihil alioquin intereſt ſi coenae dominicae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum ſtantes aut ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, aut ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus flexis percipiamus, modo inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Domini conſeruetur &amp; occaſio ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur. Vide etiam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter locos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes, fol 193.</note> otherwiſe it makes no matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ſtanding, or ſitting, or kneeling, ſo that the Lords ordinance be kept, and that occaſion of ſuperſtitions may be preuented. And this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be penned by him after his booke ſet forth againſt <hi>Stephen Gardiner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue heard ſome reply that <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> is yet againſt vs, becauſe he ſaith, it makes no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whether of the geſtues be vſed; and yet our Law bindes to kneeling onely. Vnto which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the former reioynders) this is to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:10"/>that the abridgement before named, citing <hi>Hooper</hi> in his ſixt Sermon, as vtterly againſt knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, his words are yet found, and by others of them alleadged no otherwiſe than thus: that hee could wiſh it were commanded by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that the receiuers ſhould doe it ſtanding or ſitting, and that ſitting rather he thought beſt. Now if either of theſe two were enioyned, the other could not be left ſo indifferent, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular man or woman might yet make their choice; therefore that could not be <hi>Peter Martyrs</hi> meaning, but that herein liberty was left to the choice of euery diſtinct Church.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Greenham</hi> alſo a worthy man for zeale and induſtry in preaching the Goſpell, and one who is alleadged in the Regiſter of oppoſites, to haue much withſtood our ceremonies in his yonger yeeres; afterward, one comming to aske his aduice, whether to ſit or kneele, at the Lords Table; it is ſet downe among his graue counſels vpon the word <hi>(Sacraments)</hi> that he gaue this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: For ſuch things let vs labour what wee may, to doe as much as we can for the peace of the Church.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2850:11"/>
               <head>Being occaſioned to write further vpon this argument, and in manner as before: thus I proceeded, firſt arguing in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the <hi>holy</hi> Communion, therefore how ſhould not the geſture which is moſt proper to <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>holineſſe,</hi> be (at leaſt) as fit as any other? Surely ſtanding or ſitting are not geſtures more fitting deuotion then kneeling is; Nay, how are they ſo much? ſeeing that, howſoeuer deuotion may concurre with them, yet it is not declared by them, but by kneeling we partly expreſſe it: therefore to bow downe and to worſhip are often ioyned together; as, <hi>O come let vs worſhip, fall downe and kneele, Pſa.</hi> 95. and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.29. <hi>All that be fat on earth ſhall eate and worſhip, and they that goe downe to the duſt ſhall kneele before him:</hi> Where we ſee, eating and worſhipping are ioyned together, and bowing downe is not ſeuered from them.</p>
               <p>1. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh, but this is a maine reaſon why we dare not kneele, leſt wee ſhould ſeeme to worſhip, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to worſhip the Bread and the Wine, becauſe our kneeling is appointed to be before them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>From whom ſhould ſeeming or cenſure be
<pb facs="tcp:2850:11"/>feared? Not from any that vnderſtand the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England, nor yet from the Papiſts; for they auerre ſtill (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our kneeling) that wee receiue but Bread and Wine: howſoeuer they wrong vs herein, yet they traduce vs not ſo much as to ſay, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to worſhip them:
<note place="margin">Lib. 4. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtia. c. 29. §. 2.</note> For <hi>Bellarmine</hi> plainely acknowledgeth, we all renounce that. And how ſhould our worſhip (by any of our ſelues) be thought to be directed to the Bread and Wine (as hauing Chriſts body in them, before we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, or whiles we are onely in the act of receiuing) when the order of the words is firſt to take and eate, before they be Sacramentally declared to become his body and bloud? Alſo the prayer going before, makes it plaine againſt all cauilling, <hi>viz. That wee receiuing theſe thy creatures of Bread and Wine, according, &amp;c. in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, &amp;c. may be partakers of his moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body and bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet we thinke we ſhould not bow downe before a creature, to worſhip God; as the Papists doe in and before their images.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>No more we doe: for our worſhip is directly to God and to Chriſt, no way vnto the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<note place="margin">Tom. 6. conera Maxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 3. cap. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>54</note> becauſe (as Saint <hi>Augustin</hi> ſaith) <hi>In ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis non quid ſint, ſed quid oftendant ſemper at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur:</hi> We conſider not what they are, but
<pb facs="tcp:2850:12"/>what they ſhew or ſignifie. And the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſuch, as it doth iuſtly occaſion our humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, when we receiue, and are about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them: for ſo our famous Diuines <hi>P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, BB. Iuel,</hi> and the <hi>Lord du Pleſſe,</hi> all of them allow of Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſaying in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98. <hi>No man eates the fleſh of Chriſt, except he firſt worſhip it:</hi> Theſe diuines all ſay plainely, <hi>We doe ſo,</hi> we worſhip him in the Myſteries, but not the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries themſelues; in the Sacrament, but not the Sacrament; the Creator in the creature ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and not the Creature. <hi>Peter Martyr loc. com. claſſe</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>pag.</hi> 863. <hi>Iuel</hi> fully to the ſame effect in his anſwere to <hi>Harding, Act.</hi> 8. <hi>diuiſion</hi> 22. <hi>pag.</hi> 404. and <hi>Morney</hi> fourth Booke of the Sacrament, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 452. Hereunto I annexe the confeſſion of two worthies among our Martirs, BB. <hi>Ridly</hi> and <hi>Latimer. Ridly</hi> in his diſputation at <hi>Oxford,</hi> anſwering Doctor <hi>Glin, pag.</hi> 1451. ſaith; <hi>We adore and worſhip Chriſt in the Euchariſt:</hi> and if you meane the externall Sacrament, <hi>I ſay that alſo is to be worſhipped as a Sacrament. Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 1458. <hi>Wee worſhip Chriſt in the heauens, and we worſhip him in the Sacrament; but the maſsing worſhip is not to be vſed.</hi> Againe, as touching the Papiſts bowing before Images, they ſay they worſhip them, becauſe by them they remember Chriſt; whereas we doe not worſhip bread and wine in remembrance of Chriſt, but wee worſhip onely Chriſt, of whom
<pb facs="tcp:2850:12"/>we are remembred by the bread and wine; and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhewes, if they ſhould worſhip ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges no otherwiſe, it were to bee accounted no i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-worſhip at all; his words be theſe: <hi>Siima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go non eſt veneranda niſi improprie,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De imag. San. lib. 2. cap. 21.</hi> § <hi>2. probatur eſt.</hi>
                     </note> quia nimirum coram illa, vel in illa, aut per illam adoratur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar, certe licebit ſimpliciternegare imagines eſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee thinke ſtill tho, that with reſpect to crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wee ſhould not bow downe religiouſly before them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>True, if wee hold our reſpect faſt to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and do not aſcend in our thoughts higher. But that which outwardly drawes our thoughts and affections more to God-ward, ſhould not hinder our deuotion in humiliation to bow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Ciuill gifts (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> well) ought to be taken from Princes with ciuill reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; therefore ſpirituall gifts, and the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which they are conueighed, are to bee receiued with ſpirituall and religious reuerence, as from the Maieſtie of Chriſt. This reaſon could neuer ſeeme to want force with mee, that the principal pledges of the price of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the higheſt Lord, require a bowing to receiue them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I anſwere, Sacraments be words viſible; if words audible, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoken to be heard,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:13"/>may iuſtly occaſion a falling downe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.25.</note> ſo may theſe alſo, but of the former wee haue an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25. A man hearing the ſecrets of his heart reuealed in the exerciſe of Propheſie, it is affirmed, and not diſallowed, that hee would fall downe on his face to worſhip God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, our bowing before the Sacrament hath in equall conſtruction no more ſhew of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, then the fact of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when (to bee affected the more) hee ſpread a letter before the Lord and before his owne eyes,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 37. v. 14. 15.</note> to be more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent in his prayer, wherein it is probable enough hee did not ſpare to kneele downe. Or how is not the obiection before made as ſtrong againſt kneeling downe to pray with a booke lying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen before one, to giue direction, and to helpe deuotion? or againſt vncouering the head to worſhip God in praier before the ordinary food ſet vpon our tables?</p>
               <p>4. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Papists by kneeling, worſhip the bread, how can we then kneele without appearance of euill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts doe ſo indeed, yet they deny their ſo doing becauſe they hold tranſubſtantiation, thereby <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would proue it to bee a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when we ſay they worſhip bread, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore need not ſay that intentionally and formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but materially they doe it. Yet howſoeuer they doe, wee may vſe it neuertheleſſe freely,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:13"/>and the geſture in vs is not liable to ſuſpition, becauſe we renounce their doctrine, and becauſe we haue no communion with them;
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.16.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the Chriſtian gentiles to ſalute one another with an holy kiſſe, albeit the practiſe of kiſſing, not onely prophanely, but ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly alſo had bin abuſed, among them before; <hi>adhibita erant aſcula in deorum cultu;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Elect. cap.</hi> 6.</note> as <hi>Lipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſhewes.</p>
               <p>5. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This geſture in kneeling to receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could neuer be fit, ſeeing we haue no warrant by Chriſt or his Apoſtles for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>This Obiection hath two parts. And touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former, Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> was cleane of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther minde; for he affirmes it (againſt the fourth Obiection) to haue an appearance of godly and Chriſtian veneration or reuerence;
<note place="margin">Beza Ep. 12.</note> and (to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere this Obiection alſo) he ſaith in old time it might be vſed with fruit and profit, <hi>vt ſupra:</hi> his iudgement alſo againſt the vſe of it now is anſwered by himſelfe before, <hi>pag.</hi> 5.
<note place="margin">Maſter <hi>Burges</hi> in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne.</hi> §. 10.</note> Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> likewiſe (a Preacher of note) at, in, or before the time of his being ſilenced, although he made one of his exceptions againſt ſubſcribing, to be about kneeling at the Communion; yet he ſaid he neuer ſtacke at it, as a thing vnlawfull to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe (ſaith hee) it is adminiſtred with a prayer ouer euery receauer, and for that it is
<pb facs="tcp:2850:14"/>not vnlawfull, and (if ſuperſtition had not ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it) vnfit to take ſuch a token of Gods fauour (as well as the fauours of a Prince) vpon our knees. Now ſuppoſe the prayer be not ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ouer euery one, but in common; and that (at the inſtant of receiuing) theſe words one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be vſed; <hi>(Take and eate this, &amp;c.)</hi> yet I would faine know, whether euery good heart cannot begge and intreate of God (at that inſtant) for Chriſt to ioyne himſelfe more feelingly to our ſoules, as the Bread and Wine are preſented and proffered ready to be taken into our bodies. And if the heart incline vnto ſuch a prayer, and if it bowe: how is it not ſeemely the body alſo, (to keep proportion betweene them) ſhould vſe the geſture of Beggers and Petitioners?</p>
               <p>Now to the other part of the Obiection (no warrant by Chriſts example or by his Apoſtles) I anſwere.</p>
               <p>Firſt, no more is there for ſitting, becauſe it is not certaine that Ieſus did ſit, no not after the Iewes common manner; the words of the Text being (as is noted before) <hi>as they did eate</hi> (not, as they did ſit) <hi>Ieſus tooke the bread, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I refer to my former writing, how Chriſts example may be vrged for vs.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there is warrant for kneeling in way of reuerence, if there be warrant then to ſit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered; for Diuines and <hi>Zanche</hi> by name, yeeld baring of the head, to be a geſture of worſhip, as
<pb facs="tcp:2850:14"/>well as bowing: and it cannot appeare likely to vs, that the Diſciples did eate the Sacrament bareheaded, more then that they did kneele.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if Chriſt did leaue a geſture ſtrictly to be obſerued, how comes it about (I would faine learne) that onely kneeling ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, as ſwaruing from Chriſts exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſitting or ſtanding, either of them, left indifferent? For ſo <hi>T.C. pag.</hi> 600. ſaid,
<note place="margin">Harmon. 4. ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod pag. 33.</note> ſitting at the Communion is not holden to be neceſſary; and the Harmony of the foure Synods in <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Liberum eſt ſtando, ſedendo, vel eundo caenam celebrare, non autem geniculan do ob</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>periculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, Chriſt in adminiſtring to his Diſciples, did not change place or romoue his body, to goe firſt to one, and then to another: will you ſay then (you may as well) that we ſhould not (as hauing no warrant by Chriſts ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple) goe from ſeate to ſeate, or from one end or one ſide of the Church or Chancell to miniſter vnto you?</p>
               <p>Sixtly, to omit other variable circumſtances mentioned before (which are of like nature with this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bucor</hi> in Epſ. to <hi>Iohn Anſte.</hi>
                  </note> as ſeemed to Maſter <hi>Bucer</hi>) wee are ſure Chriſt did adminiſter in vnleauened bread; therefore ſcruple might be made as well about this, as about the geſture; and as <hi>Beza</hi> reports,
<note place="margin">Beza in Gita Caluim.</note> Maſter <hi>Caluin</hi> did make ſcruple of it once, not becauſe he would vſe it, but becauſe he would
<pb facs="tcp:2850:15"/>not haue it vrged (their cuſtome hauing beene in <hi>Geneua,</hi> to communicate in common bread before; yea he left the Citie, rather then hee would be tyed to miniſter it ſo; yet (ſaith <hi>Beza</hi>) after he returned the ſecond time, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer moue contention about it, and he did feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly admoniſh others (who began to take ſuch offence at it, that they thought they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not communicate at all) to thend they ſhould no longer <hi>(ob iſtud</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>litem mouere)</hi> make ſturres for that indifferent thing; ſo hee then rearmed it, howſoeuer he thought otherwiſe of it before.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly, I anſwere, we are no more bound to the geſture at the firſt inſtitution, then we are to obſerue the time in the receiuing, becauſe (if the geſture were as is commonly ſuppoſed) one was occaſionall and accidentall, as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The time for the paſſeouer you will ſay, was occaſion for the one: and then may the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for the paſſeouer appeare as well to haue beene occaſion for the other.</p>
               <p>6. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt ordained this Sacrament to be for a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, to witneſſe our fellowſhip with him and our ioyes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>Yet we ſhould remember, that God is feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in prayſes,
<note place="margin">Exod. 15.11. Pſal. 2.11:</note> and that we are commanded to reioyce with trembling; and that the Saints of
<pb facs="tcp:2850:15"/>the heauenly banket, in the Church triumphant, are not onely ſaid to caſt off their Crownes (as we now are content to put off our hats) but alſo to fall downe and worſhip him,
<note place="margin">Apoe. 4.11.</note> that liueth for euermore, <hi>Reuelation</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>Stephen</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into ſo great grace with God that he ſaw heauen open, and Ieſus ſtanding, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Acts 7.</note> yet he fell on his knees to pray before him, and ſo ended this life.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, I cannot thinke we ſhould doe beſt to take ſtate vpon vs, when wee are about acting of it; for which we are moſt humbly to prepare our ſelues before. And when as wee confeſſe a little before, that we are not worthy to gather vp the crummes vnder his table: is it meete we ſtand vpon tearmes (when he offers himſelfe to be our food) as that we ought not to bow to him? The bitter remembrance of our ſinnes, a little before profeſſed by vs: ſhould we ſo ſlacke it, and as it were forget it in the act of receiuing, that whereof our ſinnes make vs moſt vnworthy, that (as ſome haue written) we may not vſe a geſture of inferiority and abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: It ſuteth not (they ſay) with a gheſt or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire of Chriſt, to kneele at his table, as if they that be the true heires indeede, were not as yet in their minority or nonage (whiles they be on earth) and ſo by the Apoſtles rule muſt be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.1.</note> and not challenge the priuiledges which may belong to them when they come to yeeres.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2850:16"/>
               <p>7. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is a Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bowing is not the fitteſt geſture to be vſed in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>It is indeede the Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, but eſpecially for the death of Chriſt, and to ſhew his death.
<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 21.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore held, that when the Lords Paſſion is celebrated, it is as well a time of mourning, and ſorrowing, and confeſſing of ſinnes; as of praiſes, and of cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon for them. And he deliuers his iudgement more plainely in another place, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ſolùm non peccamus adorando, ſed pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus non adorando:</hi> we ſin not if we doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Chriſt (when we are about to eate his fleſh) but on the other ſide, we ſinne if we doe not worſhip. If mens iudgements now adayes be vrged againſt it, I neede not to be aſhamed of this mans iudgement (far more ancient) for it.</p>
               <p>8. Obiection.</p>
               <p>Eightly, it is obiected, that theſe tearmes (of the Lords table,
<note place="margin">Abridgement <hi>Lyncoln.</hi>
                  </note> and of eating and drinking) make ſtrongly againſt kneeling, it being no where the cuſtome to kneele at meate, and they that vrge this argument moſt, preſſe the vſe of tables, as if we did not vſe tables for our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions: for what end elſe is Maſter <hi>Foxe</hi> and Doctor <hi>Fulke,</hi> and other Diuines alleadged to proue the old communion tables were made of
<pb facs="tcp:2850:16"/>boords? and ſo placed, that men might ſtand round about them? And whereas the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> (when he was Deane of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>) in his booke againſt <hi>Hill, pag.</hi> 38. mentions an extraordinary celebration of the Communion in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and how 30000. did communicate vpon 300. Tables, ſet vp in the fields; this is alledged by the ſilenced Miniſters of <hi>Lyncolneſhire,</hi> as the <hi>Bohemians</hi> manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, which they did vſe; and with all, to ſhew the ancient vſe of receiuing the Communion ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>I anſwere to the laſt firſt. Neither is the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians</hi> vſe and manner here related (in the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony cited of a fact extraordinary,) neither can the mention of ſo many Tables enforce that the Communicants (at leaſt many of them) did not kneele: as for the <hi>Bohemians</hi> common vſe,
<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> it is ſet down before (in their owne confeſſion) to be by kneeling: and touching mention that is made of ſtanding about the Tables; the word is ſo vſed ſometimes as no particular geſture can be determined by it; for in beginning of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing the prayer which <hi>Salomon</hi> made to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Temple, it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22.
<note place="margin">1. Kings 8. Verſe 22.</note> that he ſtood before the Altar of the Lord, and ſtretched forth his hands, and ſaid, <hi>O Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Yet againe, in <hi>verſe</hi> 54. wee reade thus;
<note place="margin">Verſe 54.</note> 
                  <hi>When</hi> Salomon <hi>had made an end of praying all this
<pb facs="tcp:2850:17"/>prayer, &amp;c. hee aroſe from before the Altar of the Lord, from kneeling on his knees, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vſuall eating otherwhere not to be with kneeling, is much obiected, and little to the purpoſe, if wee vnderſtand and conſider, how different the end and intent is of eating at or before the Lords Table, from the vſuall intent of eating food otherwiſe. Likewiſe, the ſetting of other meate vpon Tables, is to be eaten by ſuch as ſit or ſtand about them, otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Communicants poſſibly can, about the Lords Table, when there are 5. hundred or a thouſand to communicate at one time: Beſides, the vrge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Table geſture, may (if one would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious) be enforced as well to bring in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of table talke, and table courteſies of one drinking to another; and for men not to be bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, but couered.</p>
               <p>9. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The geſture of kneeling is held not to be enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in reſpect of any lawfull or conuenient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence due to the Sacrament; becauſe it is not required in the act of Baptiſme, vnto which as much reuerence is due, as to the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer reuerence were meete to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the parties that receiue Baptiſme: they are ſuch now in all Chriſtian Churches, as muſt be held vp by others, and cannot kneele
<pb facs="tcp:2850:17"/>themſelues. Secondly, it is a left-hand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to ſurmiſe; as if by this geſture wee meant (like the Papiſts) to magnifie this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more highly then the other; when as the reaſon is cleare on the other ſide, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts doe not charge vs for prophaning Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, as they doe in ſaying wee make no more account of Bread and Wine in the Euchariſt, then of Bread out of the bake-houſe, and of Wine out of the cellar, who are ſenſibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by our reuerent geſture (extraordinarie from that wee vſe in all other feeding.) And (if we ſtand ſtiffe to vſe but the ſame common geſture) it may be taken of them as a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſcandall, they would enforce againſt vs. Now I ſee not what Religion or pollicie ſhould be in it, to feede them (as one ſaith) with ſcandals, as dogs be fed with bones. To yeelde them any colourable pretence to be clamorous; as it is no way to winne them, ſo it is no way to retaine thoſe that are weake, from falling to them.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, if this order were not, and were not ſtrictly enforced, (to kneele) it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (in theſe prophane times) the holy fymboles or Sacramentall ſignes, and the whole Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would be prophaned much more then they be: <hi>ſunt enim haeres ſanctae venerandaeque:</hi> theſe things are holy, and to bee taken with veneration (ſaid the <hi>Heluetians</hi> in their former
<pb facs="tcp:2850:18"/>confeſſion:) to anſwer the cauillation of ſome, who thought they did <hi>parum tribuere ſacris ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide ſupra. pag. 4. in fir.</note> yeeld too little to the Sacramentall ſignes.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Obiect. <hi>Yet it is groſſe hypocriſie (ſay the</hi> Lynconians <hi>commended by</hi> Robinſon <hi>the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, for their zeale in this cauſe) to pretend more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence in receining, then was vſed by the Apoſtles in Chriſt his owne preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We read not that the Apoſtles did euer kneele to Chriſt while he was with them; muſt we then neuer? Againe, we haue no ground to coniecture that they ſate vncouered before him; how then (by this reaſon) may we? Father, he ſaid then he was among them as one that ſerued;
<note place="margin">Luk, 22.27.</note> I trow we doe not ſo reckon of him now. They, for hauing his preſence bodily before their eyes, as ſome ſay, it ſhould haue occaſioned their knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the rather (and then they muſt alwaies haue beene kneeling,) ſo I reaſon on the other ſide: they (becauſe of his preſence before their eyes) needed not ſuch outward helps (as we may now need) to poſſeſſe their ſoules with reuerence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; for it is prudently and iudiciouſlie affirmed by S.
<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pro mortuis cap. 50. tom. 4. coi. 884.</note> 
                  <hi>Augustine,</hi> that by meanes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall geſtures performed viſibly, the inward &amp; inuiſible intention which ſtirs them vp, is much increaſed.
<note place="margin">Cum genua fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt.</note> And (ſpeaking of bending the knees and proſtrating the body) I know not (ſaith he) how, <hi>Hi motus corporis fieri, niſi motu animi non poſſunt: tamenijſdem rurſus externis viſibiliter fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct is, ille interior inuiſibilis (quieos fecit) augetur,
<pb facs="tcp:2850:18"/>ac per hoc cordis affectus (qui vt fierentista praeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit) quia factaſunt creſcit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Ob. <hi>The vrging of kneeling at the receit of the Sacrament, is a humane preſcript for Gods worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is a diuine preſcript for man to kneel in Gods worſhip,
<note place="margin">Paeg. 101</note> or at leaſt to warrant that he may kneele. And it is proued before, that it is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient in receiuing, to worſhip God and Chriſt; therefore it is not to bee reiected as a meere hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane preſcript, to apply the geſture (hauing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe warrantize in other parts of Gods worſhip and ſeruice) vnto this part alſo, euen according to Maſter <hi>Caluins</hi> definition of a Sacrament,
<note place="margin">Caluin Inſtit. l. 4. c. 4 ſect. 1.</note> where he ſaith; It is a teſtimony of diuine grace in vs, or toward vs, confirmed by an externall ſigne, with a mutual teſtification of our piety and ſeruice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, as the Paſſeouer is called a ſeruice,
<note place="margin">Exod. 12.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 26. And whereas we profeſſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to offer vp our ſelues to God a liuing, holy and acceptable ſacrifice, ought not the ſame to be done indeed as wel at the inſtant when he offers himſelfe vnto vs? I thinke then chiefly.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Obiect. <hi>To kneele in receiuing, though it be not to worſhip God otherwiſe then hee hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: yet it is to worſhip him otherwiſe then hee hath appointed in this thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe be like squirrell ſhifts to leape from bow to bow, and at length to faſten vpon a trembling twig where ſhee catches a fall; for it is clear, ſome things outwardly belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to Gods worſhip haue beene allowed, though they haue not been required: as God did not appoint <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2850:19"/>to build him a houſe,
<note place="margin">1. King. 8:18.</note> yet the Lord did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him that hee was ſo minded. So ſeauen daies onely were required to celebrate the feaſt of the Paſſeouer, yet the aſſembly vnder good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> agreed together to keepe it other ſeuen daies,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 30.23</note> 
                  <hi>id eſt,</hi> 14. daies in all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I anſwer, that to pray before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, is no preſcript in the Word at the time of adminiſtring it, yet both is lawfull, then, and at weddings, and at burialls, neither doe wee feare that for ſuch vſage the Lord will ſay to vs one day (vpbraidingly) who hath required this at our hand?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I take it to be a generall <hi>(tenet)</hi> in the Church or Churches of Chriſt, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God may bee fitted with circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as by euery Church ſhall bee thought conuenient for the farther gracing and adorning of them, which are (in right) no more to bee counted an addition to Gods word, or Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, then it is an addition to the ſhape of a man to be arrayed in ſeemely apparell; in which ſaying (full out) we haue Maſter <hi>Caluin</hi> to ioyne with vs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caluin Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 10.</hi> §. 29.</note> whoſe words be theſe; <hi>Wee ſhall account that to be comelineſſe, which ſhall be ſo meet for the reuerence of holy myſteries, that it bee a fit exerciſe to godlineſſe, or at leaſt ſuch as ſhall ſerue for conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient garniſhing thereof, and the ſame not without fruit, but that it may put the faithfull in minde, with how great modesty, religiouſneſſe, and rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="tcp:2850:19"/>they ought to handle holy things.</hi> I grant that in the ninth ſection of the ſame Chapter,
<note place="margin">§. 9.</note> he ſaith it was a iuſt cauſe for him to impugne ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, becauſe the Authors define the worſhip of God to bee conteined in them; but this hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planes his meaning afterward, Sect. 15. of the worſhip of God, ſaying,
<note place="margin">§. 15.</note> they were accounted as ſacrifices to clenſe ſinne, and to obtaine righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſaluation, and that the neceſſity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of keeping them, was not onely referred to a generall end, but was reckoned to confiſt in the things commanded (in the end of the fifth Section:)
<note place="margin">§. 5.</note> which cannot fitly bee applied to our ceremonious geſture of kneeling, or to other of our ceremonies controuerted, of which plainly that neceſſity (whereby they are vrged) reſpects onely generall ends of reuerence, ſeemelineſſe, and vniformitie, not as if God would not, or could not bee pleaſed without them:
<note place="margin">Vrſinus part 3. doct. Chriſt. in fine 2. peacepti. ob. 3. pag. 739.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not to bee eſteemed as eſſentiall parts of Gods worſhip, but as things that belong accidentally thereunto. The end of vrging them is ſpecified before, and therefore is ſtrictneſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for obſeruance, becauſe of the contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; confuſion which cannot be auoyded, if (as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith) it ſhould bee lawfull for euery man to change thoſe things that belong to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtate:
<note place="margin">§. 6.</note> they are not aduiſed ſure that would haue it left indifferent at leaſt, for who liſt to kneele, who liſt to ſit, who liſt to ſtand:
<note place="margin">Page. 6.</note> but of
<pb facs="tcp:2850:20"/>this heretofore, <hi>Beza</hi> is alſo plentifull to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in <hi>Epiſtola</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>13. Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet godly Diuines would haue ceremonies most pure according to Chriſts inſtitution or example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this obiection is nothing to the purpoſe in this caſe, there beeing no inſtitution, nor cleare example for one geſture more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I anſwere. Godly Diuines would not haue contention or oppoſition maintained in the Church for things indifferent, or that may be tollerated when they are once growne to bee in vſe.
<note place="margin">Caluin. Epiſt. 118. 120.</note> M. <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, that diuerſity of rites and vſages in one and the ſame Church well compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ordered, is not tollerable in <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. wherfore he ſaith, he wiſhed <hi>Hooper</hi> not to ſtand out as he did about Cap and Rochet, <hi>Epist.</hi> 120. <hi>Beza</hi> in conference with <hi>Iacobus Andreas,
<note place="margin">Colloquiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mon. pelgartenſe.</note> pag.</hi> 425. ſaith, <hi>Non repugno quin coena Domini in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari celebrari poſsit.</hi> I gaine-ſay not, but that the Lords Supper may be adminiſtred vpon an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.
<note place="margin">Zanchus lib. 1. de cultu dei ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno, col. 485.</note> And <hi>Zanche</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quta neque Chriſtus, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Apoſtoliprohibueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t altaria, aut mandarunt vt menſis ligneis vteremur, idcirco inter adiophora hoc quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> annumerandum eſt.</hi> If Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> had beene altogether ſo indifferent to the Church of England,
<note place="margin">Beza in expla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. pag. 25.</note> as he was to his neighbours of <hi>Zurich,</hi> I cannot thinke but he would haue written as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably
<pb facs="tcp:2850:20"/>concerning our vſe of kneeling, as hee did of their vſe, to receiue from their Miniſters with their mouthes, and not with their hands. He ſaith indeed that vſe came vp from a ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious veneration of the ſignes (&amp; the originall of kneeling he makes to be better, <hi>vt ſupra:</hi>) hee ſpares not to call it monſtrous, when an opinion of worſhip concurs with it; yet he yeeldeth, that whatſoeuer is rightly done (as <hi>viz.</hi> to aboliſh ſuch a vſe) is not ſimply and abſolutely neceſſary: therefore they that ſo vrge taking with the hand, that they hold it a prophanation to receiue it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-way (when receiuing with the mouth only is without impiety and ſuperſtition, and vpheld to auoyd the perill of innouation.) I am afraid (ſaith Maſter <hi>Beza</hi>) they that cenſure it ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doe themſelues rather offend or ſinne by ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, of what is fit to bee held in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or elſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of pertinacie, and ſelfe-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, if wee may reaſon as Maſter <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin</hi> doth,
<note place="margin">Harmon. 4 lib. pentateuch.</note> writing vpon the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>page.</hi> 286. for the lawfull vſe of ſuch Churches or Temples as haue formerly beene defiled with Idolatrie: <hi>Quia nos non obstringit quod propter conſequentiam vt loquuntur legi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum eſt;</hi> which to my vnderſtanding, is <hi>q. d.</hi> the abuſe of a thing doth not reſtraine vs from making a lawfull vſe vſe thereof.</p>
               <p>I ſee not (by this reaſon) how any Popiſh
<pb facs="tcp:2850:21"/>abuſe of kneeling, ſurplice, or the Croſſe, can vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly make vnlawfull the vſage of them, ſo as in our Church they bee enioyned. And if (vnder name of taking away what may nouriſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition) wee ſtand preciſely to vrge remouing of ſomewhat which is <hi>per ſe medium,</hi> in it ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different: M. <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith ſaith, wee may <hi>eſſe in nimio rigore ſuperſtitioſi,</hi> our ſelues become ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious in too much ſtrictneſſe, like him that did <hi>caleare faſtum Platonis alio faſtu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, I know not whom our Church of England are to eſteeme for more godly Diuines, and free from all partialitie, then the two pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique profeſſors in the two Vniuerſities in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Martyr:</hi> who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they had not beene formerly accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the vſe of our Engliſh ceremonies) yet (beholding them) they did in no wiſe dehort from them, but perſwaded the vſe of them (as their letters extant doe ſhew:) and partly for this reaſon,
<note place="margin">Bucer in ſcript. Anglic. fol. 708 Hooper.</note> becauſe (as <hi>Bucers</hi> words be) it is euident that Ieſus Chriſt our Lord did onely preſcribe the ſubſtance of the miniſtring both of the word and Sacraments in his owne words, and al other things which pertaine to the decent and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adminiſtration of his myſteries, hee hath left and admitted to be ordered by his Church: and hence (ſaith he) we celebrate the Lords Supper, neither in the euening, nor in a priuate houſe, nor leaning, nor yet with men onely. Maſter <hi>Beza</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2850:21"/>to this purpoſe ſaith againe,
<note place="margin">Beza Epiſtola. 8. pag. 71.</note> That whatſoeuer was performed by the Apoſtles in rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, he did not iudge that forthwith it muſt bee followed for a rule without adding or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; becauſe in the beginning the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues could not determinately ſet downe all what they iudged to be expedient for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and therefore they did neceſſarily proceed by little and little, as appeares by their inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Deacons, and their practiſe ſo often, and in ſo many things of the Iewiſh ceremonies.</p>
               <p>Heereto I may adde that which another hath declared more at large,
<note place="margin">Sprint in his Caſſander.</note> how the Apoſtles did ſome things for the peace of the Church, &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the Goſpell, which in ſome other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects they did cenſure moſt hardly;
<note place="margin">Acts 16.3.</note> for S. <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> although hee profeſſed to the Galathians, If they were circumciſed,
<note place="margin">Galat. 52.</note> Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing. He made vowes, ſhaued his head,
<note place="margin">Acts 18.18. chap. 8.26.</note> &amp; was purified after the Iewiſh manner, and yet he called ſuch obſeruations im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and beggerly rudiments, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.9. The Apoſtles alſo did impoſe ſome things, (tearming them neceſſary, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. as to abſteine from bloud and that which is ſtrangled) yet I hope we ioyne not with thoſe ſectaries, who would bring the Church into ſuch bondage againe.</p>
               <p>I wiſh hartily too, that among other godly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines they were not neglected (I meane in their reaſons) whoſe direction otherwiſe by authority
<pb facs="tcp:2850:22"/>is preſſed vpon vs, by law; for the Preface before the booke of Common Prayer, ſeemes to me to be ſo penned, as may giue all ſyncere Chriſtians (void of preiudice) good ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I cannot but think it dangerous to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus, that becauſe Popery is Antichriſtianity, therfore it ſhould be a good rule in reformation, to ſhew our ſelues vnto them moſt oppoſite; for this falſe-light (like <hi>ignis fatuus</hi>) ſeemes to haue deceiued the old Arrians, who would not entitle the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt to be eſſentially God, that ſo they might be moſt vnlike the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, who profeſſedly did worſhip manie gods. Then, the eagernes to be moſt oppoſite to <hi>Arius,</hi> made ſome to be Tritheits, accounting the three perſons to be three gods: and ſome to hold with <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> that the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt were but meerely names, and did not note out ſo much as a threefold diſtinction perſonall: and to conclude (in ſtead of inſtancing farther of old) wee cannot deny but the Separatiſts (vpon this ground) are departed from vs; and (if the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be ſound) we ought all to goe out after them. <hi>Sed Deus meliora, qui facit vnanimes in domo; cui in domo ſua ex pietate &amp; concordia ſuorum, ſit laus &amp; gloria in ſacula ſeculorum.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2850:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
